<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>troughs on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/troughs/</link><description>Recent content in troughs on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 16:34:47 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/troughs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I.5.3/16</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.v.3/16/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 16:34:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.v.3/16/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
Garden Hospitium garden, possibly planted in antiquity.
Keywords archaeological garden lararia stables (animal housing) troughs (containers) Garden Description This site had been destroyed in antiquity and probably had been a hospitium. Excavated in 1874, the remains of a watering trough for animals and a stable were uncovered. Often demolished sites were planted but it could not be determined if there was vegetation present at the time of the eruption. The west wall contained an arched lararium niche.
Dates Excavated 1874.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 25, no. 34. Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, pp. 452-453. (worldcat) Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 33. (worldcat) Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 16. Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 31 March 2021</description></item></channel></rss>