<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>aedicules on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/aedicules/</link><description>Recent content in aedicules on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 16:01:37 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/aedicules/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I.7.7 House of the Priest Amandus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.7/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 16:01:37 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.7/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
Keywords aedicules atriums cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) lararia peristyles (columnades) porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia Gardens House of the Priest Amandus.
Garden Description One step above the level of the triclinium of this small house with an irregular floor plan was a peristyle garden. It was to the west of the atrium and enclosed on the north and east by a portico. Five columns supported the portico and two engaged columns on the west wall continued the order of the peristyle. A large tree root cavity (the cast measures 0.80 x 0.82) indicated that the garden was well shaded and nail holes in the wall would suggest that vines had been trained to grow in that area. A large window located in the room to the west gave a view into the garden. A puteal was located over the cistern opening in the northwest corner of the peristyle and another puteal was additionally found in the garden as well as a cartibulum (tables) decorated on one side with lions heads and a small circular base most likely used for a statuette. A lararia] on the west wall consisted of an aedicula façade with an arched niche.
Dates Excavated 1912 and 1924.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 25, no. 39.
Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, p. 30. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, pp. 37-38. (worldcat)
Maiuri, A. 1939. NSc, pp. 26-27 and fig. 1 (plan) on p. 4.
Maiuri, A. 1939. Pompeii, p. 112. (worldcat)
Maiuri, A. 1961. “I giardini,” In Le Vie d’Italia, p. 1138, no. 9.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 April 2021</description></item></channel></rss>