<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>aedicula on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/aedicula/</link><description>Recent content in aedicula on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 17:13:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/aedicula/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I.2.24 Officina Libraria</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.ii.24/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 17:13:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.ii.24/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
Keywords aedicula amphorae atrium caupona flowerpots lararium portico triclinium Garden Garden serving a caupona.
Garden Description The garden east of the atrium had a portico extending along the south and part of the west sides. A low wall (0.52m high) connected the columns and an entrance to the garden was located on the west. In 1873 the caupona was excavated. The garden contained a masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.85m; l. summus and l. imus, 3.20m) with a table. The badly damaged triclinium revealed the amphorae used in its construction. A low podium along the north wall was thought by Fiorelli to have held flowerpots. Mau reported a drainage channel at the corner of the triclinium formed by the l. meduis and the l. summus, although it is no longer evident. The base of an aedicula lararium remains against the east wall opposite the north end of the east couch.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 23, no.17
Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, p. 47 (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 1874-1877, col.60
W. F. Jashemski, 1979, Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, p. 179 (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 25 (worldcat) Mau, A. 1873. BdI, pp.245
Mau, A. 1874. BdI, pp. 253-256, 262-263
Mau, A. 1907. Pompeii: It&amp;rsquo;s life and art, p. 404
Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. II, p. 77
Soprano, P. 1950, &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, Napoli, Gaetano Macchiaroli, Editore, p. 292-293, no.1
Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 13 (worldcat)
Warscher, T. 1937-1957. Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, no.32 (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Excavated 1872.
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 14 March 2021</description></item><item><title>I.2.16</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.ii.16/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 16:05:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.ii.16/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
Keywords aedicula lararium portico Garden Peristyle garden with decorative elements.
Garden Description This house was excavated in 1873. The entranceway led directly to the portico which enclosed the garden on the north and east. In the northwest corner of the portico a masonry aedicula lararium formed an arched niche on top of a solid podium. A low wall connected the columns and pillars of the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the east side and a gutter along the east and north edges of the garden. A terracotta statuette of a seated old man holding a scroll in his right hand and wearing a short sleeved tunic (0.60 m high; Mus. Naz. Inv. No. 109 622; Ruesh no. 453) served as a fountain. This statue has been variously identified, but most likely was the Greek philosopher Antisthenes (ca. 445-360), a devoted follower of Socrates. A terracotta puteal was also found in the garden.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 22 (worldcat)
Curtius, L. 1994. Miszellen zur Geschichte des greichischen Porträts, RM, p. 38
Dwyer, E.J. 2010. Pompeii&amp;rsquo;s living statues: ancient Roman lives stolen from death, p. 128 (worldcat)
Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, p. 43 (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s. (1874-77), cols. 46, 177-179 and plate 6
Ippel, A. 1939. Statuetten aus Pompeji. AA, pp. 367-368
W. F. Jashemski, 1979, Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, pp. 48 (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, pp. 22-23 (worldcat)
Kapossy, B. 1969. Brunnenfiguren der hellenistischen und romischen Zeit, Zurich, p. 47 (worldcat)
Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. III, plate 12
Erich Pernice and Franz Winter, 1925, Gefässe und Geräthe aus BronzeDie Hellenistische Kunst in Pompeii, 5, p. 34
Richter, G. 1960. Greek Portraits, pp. 33-34, fig. 133 (worldcat)
Richter, G. 1984. Portraits of the Greeks, p. 181 and fig. 1056 (worldcat)
Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, pp. 12, 79 (worldcat)
Von Rohden, H. and Otto, L. 1880. Terracotten von Pompeji, pp. 21, 44-45 and plate 32 (worldcat)
Warscher, T. 1937-1957. Codex Topographicus Pompeianus (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Excavated 1872.
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 14 March 2021</description></item><item><title>I.2.10 House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Volusius Faustus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/ii.ii.10/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 14:06:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/ii.ii.10/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
Keywords aedicula biclinium drain lararium triclinia Garden Garden at the rear of the House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Volusius Faustus.
Garden Description The garden at the rear of the house, excavated in 1873, is almost totally destroyed. According to Mau, most of the garden was occupied by a large pool (5m X 2.90m) which was sloped toward the west from where it drained into the street through a pipe. The pool was surrounded by a low wall about 0.55m high leaving only a narrow space between the pool and the walls. In the northwest corner were the two beds of a masonry biclinium which sloped toward the wall, as was customary. Rainwater falling on them was carried away by a terracotta drain which emptied into the pool. A square niche under the north couch provided a storage space. On the wall above this couch was a rectangular niche lararium with a roughly made aedicula facade. At the east end of this couch was a masonry table. Fiorelli reports a planting bed attached to the rear (east) wall. There was a view from the triclinium through the large window in the east wall, across the pool to the garden painting on the rear wall.
When this garden was excavated in 1873, the excavators reported three panels on the east wall with garden paintings. The center panel had a body of water with swimming fish with assorted animals in the background that included a grazing deer and a springing leopard. The two panels on either side each had a large crater-shaped fountain surrounded by thick growth. Large red flowers and yellow apples could be identified to the left of each fountain and the right, pomegranates (Punica granatum L.) Jashemski examined this painting in 1964 to find it had been covered by a growth of ivy which had destroyed most of the painting. A section of a large pomegranate bush was all that was left intact at the time. She describes the leaves, painted in blue-green with darker shading and a few yellow leaves and the fruit, deep yellow with reddish-orange shading, as being rendered in an impressionistic manner. At the right of the entrance to the garden area was a cistern opening.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 22 Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, p. 42 (worldcat)
W. F. Jashemski, 1979, Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, pp. 110-111 (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 22, 313 (worldcat)
Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. II, p. 76
Schefold, K. and Dräyer, W. 1956. Pompeji, p. 9 (describes this painting as a paradeisos, with sea, deer, panther, and a nymphaeum)
Sogliano, A. 1879. Le pitture murali campane scoverte negli anni 1867-79, p. 224, no.694
Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 11
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Excavated 1873. Bombed in 1943.
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 13 March 2021</description></item><item><title>II.ii.2 (House of D. Octavius Quartio)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ii/ii.ii.2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 13:04:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ii/ii.ii.2/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula II
Keywords atrium impluvium peristyle portico biclinium aedicula triclinium insula nymphaeum pergola arbors amphorae water supply systems fountains House House of M. Loreius Tiburtinus [Della Corte]; of D. Octavius Quartio [Spinazzola]
Garden Large garden planted with trees and decorated with a water channel (euripus), garden paintings, garden statues, and a biclinium and triclinium](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300004359). Inside, a spacious peristyle with fountains was decorated with flowers in planting boxes and ornamentals.
Garden Description A. The spacious Tuscan atrium of this luxurious house excavated in 1918-1921 was a lavish garden. A low, double masonry wall, faced with marble on the outside, bordered the impluvium and according to Spinazzola, the space between the walls had been lined with wood to form a planting box for flowers and ornamentals. The pool had a fountain base, which may have held a statuette, and bases in the center of each side may have held additional statuary. On the north side of the impluvium pipe remains, as well as the cavity where the pipe emerged from under the south base, were excavated. Bombing during WWII extensively damaged the other two sides but these have since been restored.
B. At the rear of the atrium a modest peristyle garden was enclosed by a portico on the east, north and west sides. The supporting columns were smooth and colored red at the base, and fluted and white at the top. A very low wall joined all of the columns. Two circular beds in the center of the garden and a bed bordering the edges with a path between, entered from the south, were shown on the large plan by Spinazzola (see p.376). Although a dot in the center of each circular bed could represent a root cavity, no mention is made of soil contours or root cavities. A glazed terra-cotta statuette of Bes, the Egyptian deity (Pompeii inv. no. 2897) and of a pharaoh (Pompeii inv. no. 2898) were found but indications were that many other statuettes from this garden had been carried away by ancient excavators.
C. A vine covered portico terrace stretched across the back of the house immediately behind the peristyle. Animal paintings decorated the north wall of the terrace. There were two panels of deteriorating images that had been quickly rendered. Lions, lionesses, tigers and leopards pursuing bulls, deer, gazelles and hares were noted by Spinazzola. Jashemski recorded seeing the faded images of a deer, lion, and a bull and several unidentified images in the west panel. She reported that the east panel was in poor condition but she could make out lions and a deer being attacked by an unnamed animal. At the east end of the terrace, between two masonry couches of a biclinium (l. imus 2.78; l. summus 3.40 m.), two columns framed an aedicula niche. To the wall right of the niche was a painting of Pyramus and Thisbe, to the left a painting of Narcissus. A marble telamon in the form of a kneeling satyr (Pompeii inv. no. 2891) found on the terrace was thought by Spinazzola to have been a fountain head. This would have stood on the aedicula with a basin on his shoulders, spilling water down into the channel. Dr. Salza Prina Ricotti disagreed, pointing out that there is no evidence of piping either in the aedicula or the statuette. The channel, or euripus, measured 1.00 m. wide and 1.40 m. deep and extended 20 m. along the terrace. The inside of the channel was painted blue and small statues were set in the narrow strip of garden along the sides. Proceeding from east to west, the statues were as follows: on the south side, the head of a bearded Dionysus (Pompeii inv. no. 2910); across the channel on the north side, the bust of a young Dionysus (Pompeii inv. no. 2918); next on the south, a lion holding a ram’s head (Pompeii inv. no. 2922); across from this, a lion devouring an antelope (Pompeii inv. no. 2929); next on the south, the mask of a woman sculptured in a console (Pompeii inv. no. 2928); opposite this, a sphinx (Pompeii inv. no. 2930); next on the north side, a seated baby satyr with head and hands raised (Pompeii inv. no. 2931)(this piece disappeared in 1960); an infant Hercules strangling two serpents (Pompeii inv. no. 2932); opposite this, a greyhound attacking a hare (Pompeii inv. no. 2934). A bearded river god (Pompeii inv. no. 2932) looked down the channel from its source, and on the base between the pillars of the portico stood a statue of the Muse Polyhymnia (Pompeii inv. no. 2917) and one of Mnemosyne (Pompeii inv. no. 2909). These two marble statues bore traces of paint. The channel was crossed by two small bridges, one crossing by the biclinium. The other crossed in front of the grand triclinium opening just off the north side of the terrace. The triclinium offered a view across the bridge to a tetrastyle pavilion. Here fountains spouted water into the channel at the edge of the plinth of the pavilion. The lower garden that extended the length of the insula could be viewed from this point.
D. A nymphaeum in the lower garden was located directly under the tetrastyle pavilion. Water cascaded into this from the pavilion and the upper channel. Brightly colored paintings of fish surrounded a marble mask of a water deity on the rear wall of the nymphaeum. Just below, seated above little marble steps where the water tumbled down to the channel, was a marble amorino holding a mask (0.236 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 20513). The narrow channel continued more than 50 meters down the length of the garden and was interrupted by three structures. Before the first pergola, three jets of water issued from two low columns and a pillar spaced evenly in the channel. The vine covered pergola covered an elaborate fountain where water issued from the center of the structure and flowed down four steps in four directions to the pool. A small pavilion was built over the next pool and the final pool had another vine covered pergola shading a jet of water near the end of the channel. Although this series of pools and channels varied, they were all connected as one feature. Spinazzola suggested that the pools were used for raising different species of fish which would have separate habitat requirements. Shade and cover for the fish would have been supplied by the pavilion and hollows in the first marble fountain.
There was evidence of long vine arbors on each side of the channel and cavities of large shade trees lined the side walls, although no measurements were recorded. On the east side of the garden by the row of shade trees, forty-four amphorae were found buried in the soil. Rows of smaller trees or shrubs filled the area between the shade trees and the arbors.
A masonry triclinium stood to the east of the first fountain and here two sculptured supports for a marble table were found. The west side of the covered passageway once had wooden benches, and near the wall at the south end of the garden a one-third life size statuette of a sleeping hermaphrodite (Pompeii inv. no. 3021) was discovered. An entrance from the Via di Castricio allowed direct access to the garden.
Bibliography Döhl, H. 1976. Plastik aus Pompeji, Habilitationsschrift, Göttingen, p.6.
W. F. Jashemski, 1979, Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, pp.46-47 (worldcat)
W. F. Jashemski, 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p.82-83. (worldcat)
Balázs Kapossy, 1969, Brunnenfiguren der hellenistischen und römischen Zeit, p.40. John Goldicutt and Norman Neuerburg, 2016, Specimens of Ancient Decorations from Pompeii, p. 119, no.20.
Erich Pernice and Franz Winter, 1925, Gefässe und Geräthe aus BronzeDie Hellenistische Kunst in Pompeii, 5, p.49.
Salza Prina Ricotti, 1979, &amp;lsquo;Triclini&amp;rsquo;, In CronPomp, 5, pp.114-115.
P. Soprano, 1950, &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, Napoli, Gaetano Macchiaroli, Editore, pp.305-6, no.25. (Address wrongly given as II.v.2 at pp.308-309, no. 37).
Vittorio Spinazzola, 1910-1923, Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, pp.407-418 and figs. 467-478, 481 on pp.409-416, 418.
Thomas D. Price and A. W. Van Buren, 1935, &amp;lsquo;The House of Marcus Loreius Tiburtinus at Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In MAAR 12, pp.151-153 and pls. 11-13.
Paul Zanker, 1998, Pompeii: Public and Private Life, pp.477-480.
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1916, 1918, 1921, 1933-35 and 1973
Contributors Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 21 February 2021</description></item><item><title>II.i.7B/8-9</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.7b-9/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:25:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.7b-9/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula I
Keywords tabernae amphorae (storage vessels) triclinium table dolium courtyard aedicula gutter stucco hearth Garden Vineyard with large masonry triclinium, treading floor and courtyard garden.
Garden Description A. The access to this garden featured an arched niche high on the garden wall located either side of the direct entrance from the street at entrance 8. A further entrance (7A) from the street was located on the east wall. The masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.60 m.; l. imus 3.20 l. summus 2.43 m.) in the northwest corner had a round table (0.55 m. in dia.) between the couches and a rectangular table (0.65 x 1.03 m.) built against the north wall. A cistern opening was found to the south of the triclinium. To the left of entrance 8, a small room was excavated in 1985 to reveal a treading floor that allowed the juice from the grapes to flow into a small dolium. This indicates that the garden was most likely planted in vines.
B. Entrance 8 opened directly into a courtyard garden. A cistern opening in the northeast corner of the garden was fed by a gutter along the east edge. To the right of the door on the east wall was a small niche lararium with an aedicula façade. To the right of this niche, a painting of Hercules was displayed in a red border. Below this was a garden setting with an altar and a crested serpent painted in low stucco relief. In the interior area of this property, stairs leading to an upper floor and a hearth in a kitchen area were located. The stairs likely led to accommodation.
Bibliography W. F. Jashemski, 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p.75. (worldcat) Halsted B. Van der Poel, Laurentino García y García, and Joan McConnell, 1986, Corpus topographicum Pompeianum Pars IIIA, p.40-41 (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1939, 1953-1955, 1983
Contributors Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Jessica Venner (https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5828-6222)
Publication date 19 February 2021</description></item><item><title>House of the Garden of Hercules (II.viii.6)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords aedicula lararia strigillation triclinia dolium Garden Description A large aedicula lararium on the east wall and a large triclinium (l. medius, 4.40 m.; l. imus 4.00; l. summus 3.80 m.; table between couches 1.00 x 1.67m.) were found in the large area attached to this humble house when excavation was started in 1953-1954. Human remains were uncovered with five gold coins, two gold rings, a strigil and seven medical instruments close to the -triclinium. Next to the shrine two terra-cotta votive offerings, a slender female winged figure (0.155 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10569) and a small draped figure with considerable red paint surviving on the drapery(figure (0.165 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10150) were found as well as a marble statuette of Hercules (ca. 0.57 high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 10138). South of the triclinium a doghouse had been built by mounting half of a dolium (0.70 x 0.50m.) on a masonry base 0.15 m. high. Further finds included a large terra-cotta funnel, but the function of this area could not be determined. Excavation by Jashemski in 1971-1972 revealed what appears to be a large commercial flower garden. Where the lapilli remained until the 1970s, the undamaged soil contours and root and stake cavities were well preserved. Circular watering depressions remained in one bed that held a small plant. Balloon photographs showed complicated bed arrangements and a path coming from the outside area to the middle of the garden where a left turn led to the triclinium and altar in front of the lararium. Fig.63, 17.7.73, Fig. 64, 8.33.73, Fig. 65, 21A.13.73 An extensive system of rain water collection and distribution had been built. Roof run off was collected in a large dolium on each side of the door and in a nearby pool. Additional water could be brought from outside sources and poured through an amphora tip in the east end of the north wall to fill a dolium](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300400601) imbedded in the northeast corner of the garden. The natural slope of the land was from north to south and the irrigation layout took advantage of this fact. When the dolium](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300400601) in the northeast corner overflowed the water ran down a channel along the east wall watering young trees planted in the channel until it fell into a second half dolium](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300400601) buried in the soil. This process would be repeated the length of the east wall and continued along the south wall. There were channels along the north and west walls and dividing all the beds in the interior of the garden. Eleven large tree root cavities were counted with dimensions of 30 cm. or more at ground level. One grew near the southwest corner of the shrine, three along the walls and seven scattered about the garden. Another huge, partially destroyed cavity about 2 m. could have been an olive tree that grew to the west of the cistern. Many other smaller tree root cavities were found, and carbonized cherries (Prunus cerasus L.) that were found here would identify at least some of these. Along the walls with the tree root cavities were terra-cotta pots similar to those found in the House of the Ship Europa (I.XV.1-3). There were well preserved vine root cavities and post cavities for the pergola over the triclinium. Most of the garden cavities that remained were for the stakes that supported the frames for the shade structures for young bedding plants. Parallel to the west wall, 3.30m away from it, a row of posts formed either a shed or an arbor with roofing support holes in the wall above. Two ancient gardening tools, a sarculum and a dolabella were found in the garden along with bones, teeth, perfume bottle fragments, and fragments of terra-cotta unguent containers. The house to this garden contained a large number of glass perfume bottles. The assessment of pollen and spores found here are shown in Jashemski (1979).
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1953-1954, 1971-1972.
Bibliography Jashemski, W. 1979. The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden, American Journal of Archaeology, 83 (worldcat) Jashemski, W. 1979. Gardens of Pompeii, vol.I, pp.279-288 and figs. 421-435 (worldcat) Jashemski, W. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii, vol.II, pp.94-95 (worldcat) Meyer, F.G. 1980. Carbonized food plants of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villa at Torre Annunziata, p.432 Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 11 March 2021</description></item></channel></rss>