<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>peristyles on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/peristyles/</link><description>Recent content in peristyles on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 09:43:48 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/peristyles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I.6.8-9</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.8_9/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 09:43:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.8_9/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
Keywords columns (architectural elements) peristyles (Roman courtyards) pillars porticoes Garden Shop property with peristyle garden and doghouse.
Garden Description This modest house had rooms opening off the small peristyle garden at the rear of the structure. The rooms had been remodeled to serve as a shop and at the time of the eruption, were in disrepair. Four columns, two of tufa, two of brick, supported the peristyle portico on the north and east sides and were connected by a low wall with an entrance to the garden on the east side. A terra-cotta puteal was located on the east side of the portico. The house to the rear was completely destroyed necessitated the building of a crude doghouse in the last intercolumniation on the east side. Keeping a dog would have prevented intruders from entering through the ruins and robbing the shop as well as the adjacent house (no. 11) where the shopkeeper most likely resided.
Dates Excavated 1912, 1926-27. Bombed in 1943.
Bibliography Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 35. (worldcat). Maiuri, A. 1929. NSc, pp. 393-395 and fig. 26 (plan) on p. 401.
Pernice, E. and Winter, F. 1925, Gefässe und Geräthe aus BronzeDie Hellenistische Kunst in Pompeii, p. 32 and plate 21.1.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 April 2021</description></item><item><title>I.6.7 Fullonica of Stephanus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.7/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 09:35:43 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.7/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
Keywords atrium houses peristyles (Roman courtyards) pillars porticoes gutters (building drainage components) Garden Fullonica of Stephanus; Fullery of Stephanus.
Garden Description This house had been converted to a fullery and the small peristyle garden to the rear probably served as a drying area. Five pillars of the portico were connected by a low, marble topped wall. This enclosed the raised garden on the east, north and west sides with a deep gutter running around the garden along the wall.
Plans Dates Excavated 1912.
Bibliography Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, p. 198. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 35. (worldcat). Moeller, W.O. 1976. The Wool Trade of Ancient Pompeii, p. 42. (worldcat)
Spinazzola, V. 1910-1923. Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, pp. 446 and fig. 493 (plan) on p. 773 and fig. 744 (plan) on p. 765.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 April 2021</description></item><item><title>II.iv (Estate of Julia Felix/Praedia di Giulia Felice)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iv/house/ii.iv/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 14:54:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iv/house/ii.iv/</guid><description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Julia Felix
Garden Three separate gardens in this property.
Keywords jet d&amp;rsquo;eau peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia Garden Description Three separate gardens were located in this property.
A. Garden A (entrance 9) occupies the entire insula and is one of the largest properties in the city. It was originally excavated in 1755-1757, stripped of its works of art and re-buried. In 1951-1952, this garden was re-excavated and restored but not published. Sixteen elegantly carved slender marble pillars support a portico which borders the peristyle garden on the west. An alcove housed a summer triclinium (l. medius, 4.00 m.; l. imus and summus 3.00 m.) with marble faced couches that looked through the portico into the garden. Between the couches a niche supplied water that ran down small marble steps to a hole at the bottom. The water re-surfaced as a jet in the middle of the triclinium. A vine covered arbor stretched along the south and east side of the garden and beyond it in bays on the east wall were raised planting beds, alternating semicircular and square. These were covered with pumice and decorated with a band of Egyptian blue around the sides and top, the middle bay having four bands of Egyptian blue. The room to the south of the triclinium had a garden representation (0.185 x 0.42 m) on the north part of the west wall on the red middle zone.
Four fish ponds connected to form a long channel (euripus) down the center of the garden. The little marble bridges that crossed the channel and covered alcoves at the bottom of the pools provided shelter for the fish and eels.
A number of statuettes were found during the two excavations of this site. More recently the pieces that were found are as follows: A marble satyr (0.475 m. preserved height; Pompeii inv. no. 8856) located at the north end of the pool, a seated terra-cotta figure of Pittacus of Mitylene (0.65 m high; Pompeii inv. no. 2181-4) found at the edge of the pool, a small marble fountain statuette of a sea crab in a shell (0.19 m wide; Pompeii inv. no. 1073/54). During the earlier excavation some of the items found were as follows: a satyr child (0.46 m high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6108), a nude youth holding grapes in his right hand and a goose in his left (0.76 m high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6342), a faun (Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6343), an old man covered with a cloth (0.49 m. high), a bird with a lizard in its beak (0.32 m. high), a marble mask of a smiling youth on a small column (0.54 m. high), and a marble relief (0.36m. long x 0.11 m. high) of an old man seated of a bench, perhaps this was a pinax. The heads of twelve marble herms, (one woman, one old man, three bearded men) were reported by PAH, but the post of only one is mentioned and only the feet of the thirteenth herm was found. A terracotta group of Caritas Romana was found in many pieces as well as multiple fragments of other terra-cotta statuettes which had been in the eleven niches in the peristyle portico. Chambalu believed the herms stood between these niches.
B. An outdoor swimming pool (8.50 x 4.50 m; 1.50 m deep) was located in the garden area in the northeast part of the insula. There were steps into the pool on the north and south sides, and an entrance (8) into the area from the side street.
C. A walled rustic garden close to entrance 8 had been planted and at the time of the excavation; rectangular planting bed contours were evident here. This included tree root cavities were noted around the perimeter of each bed and four rectangular water basins (one of which was double), and a cistern opening.
Plans view form the portico detail of the jet. portico and garden Dates Partially excavated 1754 to 1757, 1933 to 1935, fully re-excavated 1951.
Bibliography Annali Dell&amp;rsquo;instituto Di Correspondenza Archeologica, 1830, p.50 worldcat
Bonucci, Da Carlo. 2018. Pompei Descritta Da Carlo Bonucc, p.219 worldcat
Bragantini, Irene. 1981. Pitture E Pavimenti Di Pompei. Roma: Ministero per i beni culturali e ambientali, Istituto centrale per il catalogo e la documentazione, 1981. 1:238 worldcat
Chambalu, August. 1895. Die weiderverschüttete Besitzung der Julia Felix beim Amphitheater in Pompeji, pp. 14-15 and plan of Weber (1757) after p. 20 worldcat
Della Corte, M. 1958. Notizie degli scavi antichita, p. 125, no. 238 (Pittakos inscription); worldcat
Dwyer, Eugene J. 1981. Pompeian Oscilla Collections: (pls. 80-130) Mainz: Verlag Philipp von Zabern, p. 279, no. 81 worldcat
Rakob, F. 1964. *Ein Grottentriklinium in Pompeji,*RM (1964), pp. 182-194;worldcat
Döhl, H. 1976. Plastik aus Pompeji, tesi di libera d tingen, pp. 8-10.
Idem, Pompeii (Novara), p. 111 worldcat
Idem, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 67, 128, and figs. 197, 212.
Jashemski, Wilhelmina F. 1979. The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1:48, p. 110 and figs. 81 on p. 47, 82 on p. 48, 83 (marble statue at north end of pool), figs. 84 (Pittacus), and 85 (sea-crab in shell) on p. 49. worldcat
Jashemski, Wilhelmina F. 1993. The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, pp. 86-88, 396 worldcat
Kapossy, Balázs. 1969. Brunnenfiguren Der Hellenistischen Und Römischen Zeit. Zürich, pp 46, 50 worldcat
Lorenz, Thuri. 1965. Galerien Von Griechischen Philosophen Und Dichterbildnissen Bei Den Römern. Mainz: Verlag Ph. von Zabern, p. 39 worldcat
Maiuri, A. 1961. I giardini, Le Vie d’Italia, no.9, p. 1139; worldcat
Maiuri, A. 1952. Statuette fittilli di Pittaco di Mitilene, Archeologia Classica, 4: pp. 55-59; worldcat
Maiuri, A. Pompei ed Ercolano:Fra case ed abitanti, pp. 74-75; worldcat
Pompeianarum Antiquitatum Historia. vol. 1, pt. 1, pp. 13, 15, 16, 18-19, 21, 28-31, 34, 37, 39 (Apr. 13, 1755-Mar. 6, 1756), and pt. 2 pp. 98, 101; worlcat
Richter, Greek Portraits, 3:34 and fig. 134; worlcat
Richter, G. M. A. 1960. Portraits of the Greeks, 1:89a. Latomus. worlcat
Rohden, Hermann. 1880. Die Terracotten Von Pompeji. Stuttgart, pp. 24, 47-48, 53, 57, 62 and plates 35.3, 36, 41.4, 47; worldcat
Ricotti, Salsa Prina. 1987. The Importance of Water in Roman Open Air Tricliniums, In Ancient Roman Villa Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, 10, Dumbarton Oaks, pp. 172-173; worlcat
Sear, Frank B. 1977. Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics. Heidelberg: F.H. Kerle, p.94 worlcat
Zahn, Wilhelm. 1828. Die Schönsten Ornamente Und Merkwürdigsten Gemälde Aus Pompeji, Herkulanum Und Stabiae, 2, pl.100 (plan) worldcat
Pleiades ID 955554415
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 6 March 2021</description></item><item><title>562.Insula or. I.2-3(B)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_b/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_b/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis I
House House 2-3
Garden B
Keywords atrium peristyles stuccoing Garden Description B. From the atrium the peristyle on the lower level was reached by way of a steeply sloping corridor. Stuccoed brick columns and a low wall 0.50 m. high enclosed the central area (b) and a large gutter collected water from the edges and conducted it to the cistern. A rectangular pool ca. 2.60 x 5.00 m. with the inside painted blue was located in the center of this area. At the rear of the pool an area paved with bipedales (tiles two feet long) covered the cellars below with an opening 1.70 x 2.20 to provide light. Jashemski noted that the paved and planted areas were reconstructed with a lattice fence between them, although she did not know of any evidence to support this interpretation.
Plans Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum) Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-3-b Images Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 2.3-2 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland) Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp.66-67 (worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 353 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1:50-51 and fig. 89 on p. 51 (worldcat) Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description></item><item><title>563.Insula or. I.2-3(C)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_c/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_c/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis I
House House 2-3
Garden C
Keywords peristyles Garden Description C. There are five rooms south of the peristyle and on a lower level beyond them is another garden (c).
Plans Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum) Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-3-c Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 353 (worldcat) Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description></item><item><title>Insula or. II</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._ii/insula_or._ii/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._ii/insula_or._ii/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis II
Garden Garden (a)
Keywords peristyles porticos Garden Description Directly south of the Great Palaestra there is a peristyle garden (a) enclosed by a portico. A pool with a low wall surrounding it is located in the center of this garden.
Plans Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum) Herculaneum - Garden (a) south of the Great Palaestra Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography Not applicable
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description></item><item><title>Casa D’Argo</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid><description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components) Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans Casa D’Argo Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat) Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat) - Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date</description></item><item><title>I.8.2 House of P. Paquius Proculus; House of C. Cuspius Pansa</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 19:02:52 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.1/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
Keywords columns (architectural elements) fountains gutters (building drainage components) oeci peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes tablina triclinia Garden House of P. Paquius Proculus; House of C. Cuspius Pansa.
Garden Description This elegant house was excavated in 1923. To the rear was a large and sunny peristyle garden with a portico on four sides supported by sixteen columns. At the northeast corner stood a lava puteal with a gutter that ran around the edges of the garden. In the center of the garden a wooden triclinium was shaded by a pergola supported by four columns. The nails and the imprint of the wooden structure of the triclinium were clearly preserved. A marble faced rectangular pool, with an apse-shaped extension to the north and a fountain jet, was located in front of the triclinium. This pool was connected to a smaller marble basin between the couches of the triclinium. An excellent view of the garden was afforded from the large salon at the rear of the tablinum with two columns at the entrance of the portico. The oecus also opened on the north portico with a fine view of the garden and the loggia above had a view of the garden as well as views to the sea and the Lattari Mountains.
Dates Excavated 1912, 1915, 1926 and 1936.
Bibliography Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, pp. 92. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, pp. 37. (worldcat)
Maiuri, A. 1929. NSc, p. 386, and fig. 18 (plan of triclinium) on p. 387, and fig. 20 (plan) on p. 389.
Maiuri, A. 1971. Pompeii, pp. 100-101. (worldcat)
Pernice, E. and Winter, F. 1925, Gefässe und Geräthe aus BronzeDie Hellenistische Kunst in Pompeii, p. 13.
Soprano, P. 1950. &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, p. 307, no. 30.
Spinazzola, V. 1910-1923. Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, p. 299 and fig. 334 (plan) on p. 297.
Warscher, T. 1937-1957. Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, appendix on water and photo no. 66.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 April 2021</description></item><item><title>I.6.2 House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 19:15:13 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.2/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
Keywords archaeological garden atriums busts (sculpture) columns (architectural elements) cryptoportici lararia loggias mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes stairs Garden House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus.
Garden Description A. A passageway from the atrium led to a modest peristyle garden visible through a window in the rear wall. A low wall enclosed the garden on the north and east sides along with five brick columns covered with white stucco and a pillar supporting the roof of the portico. A large, well preserved wall painting survived on the west wall of the north portico as well as a niche lararium decorated with a painted bust of Mercury. From the garden a flight of stairs led down to an elegant cryptoporticus(underground portico) illuminated by light from the adjacent garden through high windows. A solarium terrace, or loggia, overlooking the large garden could be reached by another flight of stairs form the east portico.
B. At the rear of the house, a large enclosed garden had been increased in size by reducing the wings of the cryptoporticus. The last owner had built a spacious loggia (5 x 20 m.) above the north wing of the cryptoporticus overlooking the garden. A high wall joined the five pillars and the roof supporting pilaster and formed windows into the garden. At the west end of the loggia was a masonry triclinium with side couches, each having a fulcrum (foot), (l. medius 4.41m.; l.summus and l. imus 4.68 m.; dia. of table 0.55m.). A large area was left open for tables or dancers, suggesting to Spinoza that this could have been a public gathering place. There were low seats in front of the side couches and extended along the terrace walls that may have been intended for children according to Soprano. A kitchen was located on the north side of the loggia. Six steps from the southeast corner of the loggia led up into the garden which had been raised to the level of the windows in the cryptoporticus. Della Corte thought that this garden had been used to raise many cabbages and leeks. The remains of eleven victims of the volcanic eruption were found in the garden.
Dates Excavated 1911-1929.
Bibliography Della Corte, M. NSc (1914), pp. 74-75, 228. Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, pp. 452-453. (worldcat) Jashemski, W.F. 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, pp. 33-34. (worldcat) Maiuri, A. 1933. NSc, pp. 256, 258-259, 272 and pl. 5 (plan). Prina Ricotti, S.P. Cucine Romana a Pompei E Come Eseguirle, pp. 268-271. Soprano, P. 1950, &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, Napoli, Gaetano Macchiaroli, Editore, pp. 294-295, no. 4 and fig. 30. (worldcat) Spinazzola, V. 1914. NSc, pp. 256, 259-262, 287, 365-368. Spinazzola, V. 1910-1923, Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, pp. 121-122, 442, 444-445, 451, 453. (worldcat) Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 16. Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 April 2021</description></item><item><title>I.5.2 Officina Coriarioum of M. Vesonius Primus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.v.2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 18:12:26 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.v.2/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
Keywords exedrae (site elements) lararium peristyle portico tablinum Garden Officina Coriariorum of M. Vesonius Primus (tannery) with a peristyle garden and large open space to the rear.
Keywords archaeological garden mosaics (visual works) opus signinum peristyles (Roman courtyards) pillars porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia Garden Description A. This tannery was excavated in 1873-1874. The peristyles courtyard had a portico to the north and east supported by brick pillars which had been most likely been built when the original house was converted to a tannery. Against the west wall there was a masonry triclinium (l.medius 4.99 m.; l.summus and l.imus 4.96 m.; table, 1.78 x 0.93 m.). The top of the triclinium table held the famous mosaic of a skull (0.45 x 0.50 m. Mus. Naz. inv. no. 109 982;; Reusch no. 163). The mosaic representing the Epicurian philosophy features a large skull over a butterfly on a wheel representing the soul and time. On either side of the skull are the possessions of both the rich and poor with a plumb line hanging over the skull indicating the equalizing power of death. The northeastern part of the courtyard was a rectangle, the north side of which was formed by the three first intercolumniations counting from the northeast corner of the north portico, and the east side by the first two intercolumniations counting from the same corner. This area was paved with opus signinum. The little area around the triclinium between the paved area and the west wall was believed to be a garden according to Mau.
B. The south half of the insula was also excavated in 1873-74. It was accessed from the back door in the peristyle] garden of the tannery by descending six steps. This was a large open area that had been cleared of previous structures. Formerly there had been five doors in the south wall leading to the pomerium but these were closed up. This area could have been used as a kitchen garden as suggested by Tatiana Warscher or for drying leather as suggested by Viola.
Dates Excavated 1873-1874.
Bibliography Brendel, O. 1934. “Untersuchungen zur Allegorie des pompejanischen Totenkopfmosaiks,” RM (1934), pp 157-179. Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, pp. 452-453. (worldcat), p. 452. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 93. Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, fig. 268 on p. 181 and p. 198. (worldcat) Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 33. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 272-275. Mau, A. 1907. Pompeii: It&amp;rsquo;s life and art, pp. 398-399. Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. II, p. 48 (mosaic). Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. IV, pp. 1-2. Sogliano, A. 1879. Le pitture murali campane scoverte negli anni 1867-79, cols. 9-10, 49 and pl. 2. Soprano, P. 1950, &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, Napoli, Gaetano Macchiaroli, Editore, p. 294, no. 3. Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 15 Warscher, T. 1937-1957. Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, plate 32 Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 31 March 2021</description></item></channel></rss>