<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>flowerpots on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/flowerpots/</link><description>Recent content in flowerpots on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 17:13:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/flowerpots/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I.2.24 Officina Libraria</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.ii.24/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 17:13:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.ii.24/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
Keywords aedicula amphorae atrium caupona flowerpots lararium portico triclinium Garden Garden serving a caupona.
Garden Description The garden east of the atrium had a portico extending along the south and part of the west sides. A low wall (0.52m high) connected the columns and an entrance to the garden was located on the west. In 1873 the caupona was excavated. The garden contained a masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.85m; l. summus and l. imus, 3.20m) with a table. The badly damaged triclinium revealed the amphorae used in its construction. A low podium along the north wall was thought by Fiorelli to have held flowerpots. Mau reported a drainage channel at the corner of the triclinium formed by the l. meduis and the l. summus, although it is no longer evident. The base of an aedicula lararium remains against the east wall opposite the north end of the east couch.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 23, no.17
Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, p. 47 (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 1874-1877, col.60
W. F. Jashemski, 1979, Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, p. 179 (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 25 (worldcat) Mau, A. 1873. BdI, pp.245
Mau, A. 1874. BdI, pp. 253-256, 262-263
Mau, A. 1907. Pompeii: It&amp;rsquo;s life and art, p. 404
Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. II, p. 77
Soprano, P. 1950, &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, Napoli, Gaetano Macchiaroli, Editore, p. 292-293, no.1
Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 13 (worldcat)
Warscher, T. 1937-1957. Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, no.32 (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Excavated 1872.
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 14 March 2021</description></item></channel></rss>