<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cistern on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/cistern/</link><description>Recent content in cistern on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/cistern/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>II.iii.4-6</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6/</guid><description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House II.iii.4-6
Garden Small domestic property with a garden to the rear.
Keywords caupona cistern lararium sacellum with an aedicula lararium statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tufa Garden Description A. A small garden at the rear of this connected house and caupona may have originally contained the two small statuettes found at this site in 1953. The two pieces were a headless ithyphallic tufa statuette (0.33 m. high with base; Pompeii inv. no. 10017) and a marble statuette of Venus (0.51 m. high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 9926) with much of the red color preserved in the drapery. The inventory books list this house as II.vi.4.
B. The small garden to the rear of house 4 had an entrance into this large open area (b) which had been planted at the time of the eruption. There was a second entrance (6) from the side street. At the time of excavation a cistern was noted in the southwest corner, a basin along the south wall just before the jog, and the presence of seven root cavities. Jashemski found a few other scattered root cavities later, but too much damage had occurred from new growth to determine the original planting plan. At the east end of the north wall a door opened to a small sacellum with an aedicula lararium on a small podium on the rear wall and a small masonry.
Dates 1754 to 1757, 1952
Bibliography Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993, pp. 84. worldcat Pleiades ID 998787235
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 6 March 2021</description></item><item><title>House of Neptune (Maison de Neptune)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/africa_proconsularis/thuburbo_maius/house_of_neptune/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/africa_proconsularis/thuburbo_maius/house_of_neptune/</guid><description>Province Africa Proconsularis
Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location THUBURBO MAIUS (Henchir Kasbat), Tunisia
THUBURBO MAIUS (Henchir Kasbat), Tunisia (Pleiades)
Location Description The city occupies the slopes of a hill in a fertile grain producing area about 50 kilometers to the south of Tunis. Originally a settlement of mercenary soldiers after the fall of Carthage, it was raised to amunicipium by Hadrian (117-138), and to a colony during therein of Commodus (177-192). The chief public buildings and the most beautiful homes date from this period. After the crisis of the Empire during the third century, Thuburbo saw a rebirth in the fourth century; but as imperial authority declined the city became a mere village.
Garden House of Neptune (Maison de Neptune)
Keywords domus peristyle houses cistern [semicircular basin] Garden Description The house was laid out around a peristyle garden (IV-VIII), with four porticos supported by twelve columns. A low wall separated the porticos from the garden (Plan view, Fig. 1). A semicircular basin extended into the garden between the second and the third columns on the SE side. The cistern opening in the garden is adjacent to the middle column on the SE side. A large reception room (XVII) had a view of the basin and the garden.
Maps Images Fig.1: Plan of the House of Neptune (CMT, Thuburbo Majus, V. II, fasc.1, pp. 141-61, plan 20-30) Dates The house dates from the beginning of the IIIrd century.
Bibliography CMT, Thuburbo Majus, Les mosaïques de la région du Forum, V. II, fasc.1, INA, Tunis, 1980, pp. 141-61, plan 20-30 Worldcat Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 240-242. (worldcat) Pleiades_ID 981504
TGN ID 7001750
Contributor [Wilhelmina F. Jashemski]
Publication Date</description></item></channel></rss>