<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>insulae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/insulae/</link><description>Recent content in insulae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 10:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/insulae/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Insula dei Dipinti</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/ostia/insula_dei_dipinti/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 10:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/ostia/insula_dei_dipinti/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Region unspecified
Location Ostia (Pleiades)
Location Description DESCRIPTION
Ostia Antica, the port-city of Rome, was situated at the mouth (ostium) of the Tiber, where it flowed into the Tyrrhenian sea. Rome was situated further upriver, several kilometres from the sea. By its maritime position, Ostia also protected the landing at the mouth of the river; it controlled the trade that ran along it, and also the production of salt in the nearby salt works. Ancient historians believed that the city had been founded in the 7thcentury by king Ancus Marcius; archaeological evidence shows that the first settlement was founded as a colonia maritima in the 4thcentury B.C. and that it was already acting as the harbour of Rome in the 3rdcentury B.C.
From the 2ndcentury B.C. Ostia (and later Portus) was the main port for the landing of wheat and other foodstuffs destined for the markets of Rome. It was a lively and cosmopolitan port city, where the great cargo ships unloaded produce from all over the Mediterranean and beyond. At Ostia the freight was transferred to riverboats to be sent upriver to Rome. This thriving commercial activity was accompanied by demographic and economic growth and by the presence of people coming from all over the known world.
Ostia is especially well known in archaeological and historical studies for its building history. The earliest Ostian houses are only known from sporadic traces, beginning from the 2nd century B.C. They were domus of traditional type, both in the simplest version, of direct Italic derivation, with rooms arranged round the atrium, and in the more complex Roman-Hellenistic form, in which the peristyle with the garden was added (e.g. the House of the Bucrania). They were single-family houses, generally single storied, or with an upper story limited to the height of the atrium.
The transition to a different type of house was marked by the so-called peristyle house, such as the House on the Via del Tempio Rotondo, which dates to the Augustan period, the one found below the Schola of Trajan (built A.D. 20-40) and the House of the Thunderbolt, datable to the Vespasianic period (A.D. 69-79). In this latter type of house the rooms are laid out around a small central colonnaded courtyard, sometimes provided with a garden, more often paved. The later examples of this type include the first phase of the House of Fortuna Annonaria, with its garden (AD 140-190).
Ostia was heavily reconstructed in the 2ndcentury A.D., under the pressure of the growth in population due to the completion of its ports. The new city followed new canons of utilitarian, high-density building, based on the multi-storied insula, which aimed at the efficient use of the little space available. A room with windows on the façade became a kind of atrium-room. The plan became enriched with smaller rooms and internal staircases that ascended to the private apartments of the upper floor. Independent stairways entered from the street provided access to the apartments on the second and upper floors. The most accomplished examples of this type of building date to the Hadrianic period, for example in some insulae that compose the so-called Garden Houses. In another type of insula the main source of light is not the street, but an inner arcaded courtyard.
The internal space was not always delimited by a portico; the Insula of the Paintings, comprising the houses of Jove and Ganymede, of the Infant Bacchus and of the Paintings, arranged according to an L-shaped plan, had its façade facing onto two streets, forming a corner, while its inner sides faced onto a fairly extensive garden, without porticoes.
In the 3rdand 4thcenturies, the tenement houses of the less well-to-do fell into ruin or were patched up. Private building seemed limited to the erection of new patrician domus (e.g. the House of Amor and Psyche), built on the ground floor of already existing buildings and richly decorated with costly marbles. In these houses the gardens were chiefly an ornamental backdrop.
The internal garden of the house at Ostia described by St. Augustine (Confessions 9.10.23), which forms the setting for the conversation with his mother St. Monica in A.D. 388, is precisely of this type: a decorative backdrop that enhanced the peace and quiet of the interior of the house, an antithesis to the frenetic but vain life of the city outside.
Ostia gives us, all things considered, the idea of a heavily built-up city, which sacrificed much of its greenery in the attempt to exploit building land as intensively as possible. This must have been the case especially in the most intensive building phase in its history (1st-3rdcentury A.D.). As a consequence, the gardens laid out before this period were in large part destroyed by subsequent building activity. Later garden layouts, on the other hand, were wiped out by the frantic campaign of excavation in the years 1938-1942, conducted in preparation for the World Exhibition, never held due to the outbreak of the Second World War. But today, thanks to the new excavations being conducted at Ostia by Italian and international research groups, using the most modern methods of investigation, the gardens of the ancient city are finally being recovered. In all the cases so far ascertained, they were gardens laid out within peristyles/courtyards, associated with wells or fountains for irrigation. In some cases, the excavators found the classic perforated vases, in others large fragments of terracotta containers. As regards garden furniture, only the Domus of Fortuna Annonaria provided some reliable data.
Ostia in ancient times, however, must have been a good deal greener and richer in vegetation and flora than now seems the case; the ancient sources in fact speak of the flourishing cultivation of vegetables, leaks, melons and salads in Ostian territory. In the 5thcentury A.D. “the Isola Sacra is so lush and pleasant that it does not lack admirable grazing land, neither in the summer, nor in the winter months; in the spring, moreover, it is filled with such a profusion of roses and other flowers that it may be called, for its luscious flowering fragrance, the Lebanon of bountiful Venus” (Cosmographia: 25.25-30).
Garden Insula dei Dipinti
Keywords aedicules flowerpots insulae mosaics (visual works) Garden Description The large open area in this insula, divided into two by a wall, was identified as a garden at the time of excavation (1914 to 1919), but on little evidence apart from the absence of paving over most of the area. Recent excavations have however clarified the phases of the garden and added some significant detail. The garden is now known to have been created as a single area, forming an integral part of the late Hadrianic development comprising the three houses which make up the Insula of the Paintings (House of Jove and Ganymede, House of the Infant Bacchus and House of the Paintings). The excavations in the SW corner of the south garden (Fig. 1, Tr. 1) however produced no evidence of Hadrianic garden features, due to the garden being greatly disturbed by a substantial restoration of the insula somewhere in the period AD 150-180. At this time the wall dividing the garden into two was built, and a humus-rich soil imported into the south garden area, its use as a garden being confirmed by fragments of five flower pots, recognized by the holes in their bases. In addition, the lower part of a Dressel 20 amphora and a neat, sub-triangular pit roughly 50 cm across cut into the underlying rubble fill may have served as planters. In the Severan period a small aedicular shrine was added to the south face of the new garden wall, the niche being originally decorated with glass mosaic above foliage plants against a red ground. This was later covered with whitewash and replaced by a figured scene, and finally a statue of Jove was installed in the niche. A section of black-and-white geometric mosaic, overlying the humus-rich soil in Trench 1 and possibly associated lightweight rough walls, suggests the creation of a summer pavilion or dining room during this period, which would have enjoyed a view of the garden shrine.
Plans Fig. 1: Ostia Antica, General Plan. Fig. 2: The Garden and Houses of the Insula dei Dipinti. Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography G. Calza, Topografia generale. (worldcat) R. Meiggs, Roman Ostia. (worldcat) C. Pavolini, Ostia: Vita quotidiana. (worldcat) Jean-Paul Descœudres, Ostia: Port et porte de la Rome antique. (worldcat) Giornale degli Scavi (Notizie degli scavi di antichità), 1917, pp. 58, 69-70. (worldcat) Giornale degli Scavi (Notizie degli scavi di antichità), 1919, pp. 227-228, 251-253, 255, 263-5. (worldcat) G. Calza, Monumenti antichi 26 (1920), pp. 328-330. (worldcat) Pleiades ID 422995
TGN ID 7007018
Contributor Janet DeLaine
Publication date unspecified</description></item><item><title>House of Grotto of catullus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</guid><description>Province Italia
Location Sirmio
Sirmio (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden House of Grotto of Aatullus
Keywords insulae cryptoportici vestibules piscinae peristyles (columnades) porticoes bathhouses (water recreation structures) atriums ditches water supply systems water baths gutters (building drainage components) drains loam basins (vessels) statues cisterns (plumbing components) terrazzo water wells orchards presence chambers fences (site elements) exedrae (site elements) garden pavilions reception rooms terrazzo Garden Description Sirmio is known from a citation in Catullus’ XXXI° poem (paene insularum, Sirmio, insularumque ocelle &amp;hellip;) and in later road itineraries as a staging post (Sermione mansio) along the road between Verona and Brixia (Brescia), which passed to the south of the peninsula, forming part of the erritory of Verona. In several areas along this ancient coastline remains have been brought to light of large and sumptuous villas built on the coast, in large coves or high places, with beautiful panoramas.The remains of a villa, called by fifteenth-century visitors to the site “Grotte di Catullo”, after Verona’s poet Catullus, are situated at the northern tip of the Sirmione peninsula, on the southern bank of the Benacus(Lake Garda), the largest of the pre-alpine lakes (Fig.1). As one of the most interesting examples of Roman residential architecture in northern Italy, this villa deserves the designation of villa maritima, as other similar examples along the Campanium-Latium coast.The villa covers an area of around 20,000 square meters distributed on three terraces, which ascend the slope of the hill on a series of substructures. The building has a rectangular plan (167.5 x 105 meters), with two foreparts; on the S side at the main entrance and on the N side at the tip of the peninsula, towards which the villa faced, so as to be surrounded by the lake on three sides (Fig. 2).On the evidence of recent studies, the villa is dated to the Augustan-Tiberian period (end of the first century B.C. –start of the first century A.D.): it was constructed after the destruction of an earlier building, the existence of which has been documented in a small archaeological excavation beneath the floor of one of the rooms on the southern side of the villa. Modifications to the building, in particular the creation of the large baths area, date to the end of the first –second century A.D. The destruction of the villa came quickly, with all probability around the 3rd century: at that time the functioning of the villa seems to have stopped and no later maintenance or building interventions have been identified; a differing situation as regards the other villas in the lake Garda area, which had a continued life, with phases of great importance, up to the first half of the fifth century.The building, constructed as a whole and with axial and symmetrical criteria, is characterized by long terraces on the eastern, western and northern sides: these connect directly with the large terrace on the northern forepart, which was shaded by a veiled covering, as demonstrated by the characteristic elements which supported the posts found in this area. By the side of the terraces were long porticoes: the western one built over a double-nave cryptoporticus, which acted as a substructure, the eastern for the main part built directly on the natural bedrock. The residential rooms were distributed in the northern and southern areas, the western part of the latter being occupied by the baths complex (Fig. 3-4).While the substructures are well-preserved, the residential floor, situated on the higher level, has been subject to greater destruction over the course of the centuries, due to the systematic robbing of building materials, already started in ancient times, the collapse of part of the wall on the eastern side along the hill-side, and in the agricultural use of the land, presently occupied by a vast olive grove (Fig. 5). The villa has been excavated on several occasions from the start of the 19th century and subsequently backfilled, so that the plan and hypotheses for the reconstruction for a large part of the residential level, which has not been the object of new research in recent years, are based on the notes and drawings of the 19th century, not always reliable. Other excavations were conducted between 1941 and 1965; research aimed at defining the chronology of the building and resolving problems in the plan of several rooms in the southern area were undertaken between 1984 and 1994.The events endured by the structure render difficult and at times impossible, at present, to hypothesize the functions and characteristics of many of the residential rooms, as also with the various open spaces present within the building. Undoubtedly, other than the large peristyle (C), which occupied the central area of the building, other open spaces, now buried (courtyards or gardens), were to be found along the central N-S axis. In the southern part there was an open space (N), situated between the western part of the villa, destined as the baths complex, and the eastern part containing the living rooms. In this case, according to the interpretation of the director of the first excavations and more recently, the area functioned as a courtyard giving access and light to the rooms on its E, S and W sides. A wall divided the courtyard from the S side of the peristyle, to which direct access was possible by one or more entrances. Another hypothesis suggests that access between the two courtyards was not axial but by a side corridor, while a wall with windows would have permitted a view of the internal garden.Of the other open space (O), situated to the N, there is uncertainty as to its function. One can hypothesize, on the basis of the 19th century plans, an open space with porticoes on all four sides: perhaps another small peristyle. An element which would confirm its use as a courtyard or garden is the presence of a stone-built rainwater drain, still present in the 19th century and illustrated by Orti Manara in his publication on Sirmione. Some parts of this drain have been re-used in the walls of the Early Medieval church of San Salvatore in Sirmione. There are no precise indications for external gardens and it is only possible to hypothesize the natural setting in which the villa was situated. However it must be stated that artificial terraces had been made on the eastern side of the building, or more precisely the areas which corresponded to the N-E and S-E corners, formed by the two foreparts of the villa. In the first (H) the bedrock has been cut to a depth of around 4 meters to create a large terrace, which occupied the whole area as far as the drop in level towards the lake (Fig.6). It is interesting that the second artificial terrace (I), of more limited extension, at around 10 meters below the residential level of the villa and reached by a flight of steps, was still known in the 19th century, by ancient tradition and without apparent justification, as “the garden.”The large central open space (C), beginning from the 19th century, was identified as a courtyard-viridarium. It is formed by an area of around 4000 square meters, equivalent to about one fifth of the whole area of the villa (Fig.7). Both the 19th century excavations and more recent trenches have failed to locate the presence of structures or floors, and it is therefore possible to hypothesize that the area functioned as a garden, probably surrounded on all four sides by porticoes as indicated in the 19th century plans and supported by recent research.The present land use, with many trees, and the thin soil cover in respect to the original ground surface, no longer permit the acquisition of data to allow a more precise reconstruction of the ancient garden, its internal sub-divisions, the types of vegetation, the possible ornamentation. On the S side of the peristyle is located a large perfectly preserved underground cistern (66), of a length corresponding to the width of the peristyle (42.60 x 2.40 meters). It is covered by a herringbone floor in small bricks, 6 meters wide and around 50 meters long (fig.8). Rainwater, collected in this part of the building, flowed into the cistern through a series of lead fistulae which entered the S-E and S-W corners, as is demonstrated by holes in the floor created by the robbing of the lead pipes, of which fortunately a small part is still preserved in the S-W corner, where it enters the cistern. The floor of the cistern has a slope of 7-8% from S to N: on the northern side four channels collected rain water and allowed it to flow in an organized manner towards the garden, with a slope of 6% (fig.9). The channel was formed in the initial part by a prolongation of the herringbone brick floor, which with its tapering form towards the external area helped the entry of rainwater into the channel, which flowed beneath the ancient ground surface (Fig. 10). The channels, lined with hydraulic mortar, were excavated in the bedrock, which outcropped on the eastern side and were covered with thin stone slabs. On the opposite side they were constructed in the earth and only their lower parts are preserved, the covering and the ancient floor shaving been robbed. Given the slope of the channels, their conformation and number, it is to be excluded that they had the sole function of draining the rainwater from the brick floor, and it may be hypothesized that they also served the function of directing to the garden the water which was extracted from the cistern, perhaps for irrigation.Water was drawn from the cistern by one or more wells: in the 19th century a well-curb, which was said to have come from the area of cistern, was still preserved in Sirmione. By the side of the cut which housed one of the well-curbs, two square holes had been cut into the floor in ancient times. It is hypothesized that they held the posts for the structure supporting the ropes and vessel used to extract water from the cistern (girgillus).There are no other elements to help describe the form of the large peristyle. Two pieces which may have formed part of the decoration of the garden are composed of sculptural fragments: a head dating to the second century A.D., found in the soil inside the cistern (66), and a sundial, presently lost, but fortunately represented by a drawing. Given the location, the head must have come from the peristyle, and can be hypothesized as belonging to the statue of a Dioscuros (fig. 11). In Greek marble, it is broken at the level of the chin. The head is covered by a pilos, from which issue locks of hair, curling on the forehead and sides of the face.There are no useful clues to help reconstruct the vegetation, which may have been present in and around the villa.The climate of Lake Garda is sub-Mediterranean, determined by the notably large mass of water which tends to maintain a constant temperature, much milder than the rest of the cisalpine area. The cultivation of olives already existed in Roman times, as documented by botanical evidence from recent excavations at Sirmione and the strong spread of the plant both in the locality and the whole area around Lake Garda in the Early Medieval period. In the same manner grapes were probably also cultivated, indirectly represented by an inscription found near Sirmione (fig. 12). Probably also common in the Roman period were the native species, shrubs such as oleander and rosemary and trees such as cypress, bay, ash and several species of oak, documented in the last two examples by botanic remains found at Sirmione, recently analyzed by the Archaeobiological Laboratory of the Civic Museums of Como.
Plans {&amp;lt; figure src=&amp;quot;../images/sirmio-2.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;ldquo;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus.&amp;rdquo; title=&amp;ldquo;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;}}
Fig. 3: Plan of the residential rooms Fig. 5: Aerial view of vast olive grove Fig. 7: Aerial view of courtyard-viridarium Fig. 11: statue of a Dioscuros Fig. 12: Figure of Plant fossils Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1801
Bibliography G.G. Orti Manara, La penisola di Sirmione sul lago di Garda, Verona 1856.(worldcat) N. Degrassi, Le Grotte di Catullo, Taranto 1956. (worldcat) M. MirabellaRoberti, La villa romana di Sirmione, Milano 1958, pp.157-162.(worldcat) T.P.Wiseman, Le Grotte di Catullo. Una villa romana e i suoi proprietari, Brescia 1990. (worldcat) E. Roffia, Sirmione, le “grotte di Catullo”, in Ville romane sul lago di Garda, a cura di E.Roffia, Brescia 1997, pp.141-169. (worldcat) Pleiades ID 870993210
TGN ID 7005771
Contributor Tom Elliott (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/thomase)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description></item><item><title>Shrine Complex in Insula E125</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/arabia_petraea/hauarra/arabia_hauarra/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/arabia_petraea/hauarra/arabia_hauarra/</guid><description>Province Arabia Petraea Arabia (province) (Pleiades)
The history of Roman Arabia begins with the death of the Nabataean king, Rabb&amp;rsquo;el II soter, in A.D. 106. The emperor Trajan annexed the Nabataean kingdom and organized its territory within the new Roman province of Arabia Petraea that occupied a large area of northwestern Arabia, extending from the Hauran in the north, to the Negev and Sinai deserts in the west, and into the northern Hejaz in the south. The administrative district of Perea, formerly under the Herodian dynasty was also added. The provincial capital of Arabia Petraea was located at Bostra which replaced Petra as the capital of Nabataea in the last decades of that kingdom’s independence. Petra continued to function as an important cultural, political and economic center of the province for at least a century following annexation. During the early Byzantine period (4th-6th centuries CE), the major cities of the Roman era continued to flourish, and Christianity gradually became the accepted religion of the area. Petra remained an important center in the early Byzantine period when it was inhabited by a substantial Christian community and was the seat of a bishopric.
The region of Arabia Petraea is primarily a desert environment that belongs to the eastern Mediterranean weather system. Its inhabitants experienced marked seasonal contrasts with dry, hot summers and cold, wet winters. Rainfall occurs during the winter months and ranges from over 600 millimeters in the north-west to as low as 100 millimeters in the south and east of the region.
Location Auara
Auara (Pleiades)
Nabataean Hawara (Auara) was founded by king Aretas III in the early first century BCE as a trading post along the King&amp;rsquo;s Highway, midway between the Nabataean capital, Petra, and the port town of Aila on the Gulf of Aqaba (Fig. 1). In the early 2nd century CE, under Roman occupation, a fort was erected at the site (Roman Hauarra/Havarra) due to its strategic position on the major trade highway that was rebuilt as the Via Nova Traiana. Associated with the fort was a small town with a bathhouse and a community shrine.
Garden Shrine Complex in Insula E125
Keywords aqueducts baetyls basins (vessels) insulae naoi (chambers) planters (containers) shrines (structures) temene Garden Description A few decades after a Nabataean shrine (Fig. 2) at Hauarra had been severely damaged during the Roman conquest of Arabia Petraea, the site’s inhabitants built another shrine at the same location. The Roman-period shrine occupied the southeast corner of a multi-unit insula (E125), but could only be accessed from outside the complex. This shrine consisted of a square naos (containing a central Nabataean baetyl and legionary altar, bins, shelves, and votive offerings) enclosed in a rectangular open-air temenos (Fig. 3). Upon entering the temenos, worshippers walked to the naos along a 12.7 m long paved processional way that was flanked by two long raised planters. An aqueduct-fed basin next to the door of the naos appears to have supplied the shrine with so much fresh water that it must have been intended not just for ritual cleansing, but for supplying the planters as well. Given the relatively shallow depth of the planters, and that no root balls or pots were found within, they probably contained shrubs and/or flowers rather than trees. Although the architect clearly tried to make the planters symmetrical in size, shape, and location, their design (and that of the whole Roman shrine) was constrained by the reuse of some Nabataean walls as foundations.
Maps Fig 1: Map showing the location of ancient Hawara (Hauarra) in Arabia Petraea (L.-A. Bedal) Plans Fig 2: Plan of Shrine Complex in the southeast corner of Insula E125 (Plan by S. Fraser and D. Skinner) Images Fig. 3: Shrine Complex in Insula E125 (Reconstruction by C. Kanellopoulos and P. Konstandopoulos) Dates 1st century CE, mid-2nd to 3rd century CE
Bibliography Oleson, J. P., M. B. Reeves, G. S. Baker, E. de Bruijn, Y. Gerber, M. Nikolic, and A. N. Sherwood. 2008. “Preliminary Report on Excavations at Al-Humayma, Ancient Hawara, 2004 and 2005.” Annual of the Department of Antiquities of Jordan 52: 309–42. (Stable URL). Reeves, M. B. 2019. “A Nabataean and Roman Shrine with Civic and Military Gods at Humayma, Jordan.” Arabian Archaeology &amp;amp; Epigraphy 30 (1): 134–55. (DOI). Pleiades ID 746716 (Auara)
TGN ID 7007646 (Ḥawwārah)
Contributor M. Barbara Reeves
Publication date 15 Apr 2021</description></item></channel></rss>