<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gutters on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/gutters/</link><description>Recent content in gutters on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 09:36:47 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/gutters/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I.6.15 House of L. Ceius Secundus; House of the Ceii; of Queen Elena; of Fabia and Tyrannus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.15/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 09:36:47 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.15/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
Keywords basins (vessels) cisterns (plumbing components) fountains garden lights garden ornaments gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) porticoes Garden House of L. Ceius Secundus; House of the Ceii; of Queen Elena; of Fabia and Tyrannus.
Garden Description This small garden was located at the rear of the house and featured a portico on part of the south side and a gutter along the south and east sides which carried water to the cistern. Preserved on the rear wall was one of the best animal paintings found in Pompeii, with three large openings provided in the painting to accommodate garden lights. On either side of the animal painting at the lower part of the wall is a garden painting with a sphinx crouching in oleanders with dark red blossoms holding a fountain basin. The fountain on the right would appear to pour water into the actual gutter below. A realistic border of myrtle (Myrtus communis L.) and ivy (Hedera helix L.) is painted along the bottom of the wall with birds flying across a red background. Just above this, branches of ivy are painted along the bottom of an expansive wild animal scene. A bull is being pursued by a lion across a rocky lake shore on the lower foreground, wolves and wild boars occupy the center of the picture on the opposite shore, on the right a leopard is chasing two rams, and two gazelles are painted on the left. Brackets for garden lights had been installed where three large holes remained in this animal painting. The outside walls of the apotheca (storeroom) on the southwest corner of the garden had painted garden motifs. There was a garden scene painted on a reddish background depicting a statue of a water nymph with a two handled basin appearing to catch water from the roof and directing it to the gutter below. To the left are bushes with a tawny owl (Strix aluco L.) and to the right is a white pigeon or rock dove (Columba livia Gmelin). Over this was a panel with two peacocks (Pavo cristatus L.) facing a bronze garden ornament that consists of a leafy stalk topped by a round shield. Flowering plants fill in the bottom while the top of the panel is graced with two garlands and two flying birds, a swallow (Hirundo rustica L.) on the left and a large headed bird on the right which could be a shrike (Lanius sp.) Although the outside wall of the apotheca was badly damaged, to the right of the window paintings of a bush with red blossoms and a myrtle bush on a yellow background survived. The east and west walls were decorated with large Egyptian landscapes. Another garden decoration, a marble dove (0.29 m. long) was found in the kitchen.
Dates Excavated 1913.
Bibliography Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, pp. 69-70, 113 and fig 43, 111-114. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p. 315. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 2002. The Natural History of Pompeii, p. 37.(worldcat) Maiuri, A. 1926. Boll. D&amp;rsquo;Arte, n.s., p. 69, fig. 112.
Peters, Landscape, pp. 172-173. (worldcat)
PPP, pp. 43-44.
Schefold, K. and Dräyer, W. 1956. Pompeji, p. 9.
Spinazzola, V. 1910-1923. Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, pp. 407-418 and figs. 467-478, 481 on pp.409-416, 418. Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, pp. 275-277, fig. 282 (plan) on p. 258, and figs. 304, 306, and 307 on pp. 275-277. (worldcat)
Zanker, P. 1998. Pompeii: Public and Private Life, pp. 477-480.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 April 2021</description></item><item><title>I.6.7 Fullonica of Stephanus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.7/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 09:35:43 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.7/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
Keywords atrium houses peristyles (Roman courtyards) pillars porticoes gutters (building drainage components) Garden Fullonica of Stephanus; Fullery of Stephanus.
Garden Description This house had been converted to a fullery and the small peristyle garden to the rear probably served as a drying area. Five pillars of the portico were connected by a low, marble topped wall. This enclosed the raised garden on the east, north and west sides with a deep gutter running around the garden along the wall.
Plans Dates Excavated 1912.
Bibliography Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, p. 198. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 35. (worldcat). Moeller, W.O. 1976. The Wool Trade of Ancient Pompeii, p. 42. (worldcat)
Spinazzola, V. 1910-1923. Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, pp. 446 and fig. 493 (plan) on p. 773 and fig. 744 (plan) on p. 765.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 April 2021</description></item><item><title>Casa D’Argo</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid><description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components) Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans Casa D’Argo Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat) Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat) - Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date</description></item><item><title>I.8.2 House of P. Paquius Proculus; House of C. Cuspius Pansa</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 19:02:52 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.1/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
Keywords columns (architectural elements) fountains gutters (building drainage components) oeci peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes tablina triclinia Garden House of P. Paquius Proculus; House of C. Cuspius Pansa.
Garden Description This elegant house was excavated in 1923. To the rear was a large and sunny peristyle garden with a portico on four sides supported by sixteen columns. At the northeast corner stood a lava puteal with a gutter that ran around the edges of the garden. In the center of the garden a wooden triclinium was shaded by a pergola supported by four columns. The nails and the imprint of the wooden structure of the triclinium were clearly preserved. A marble faced rectangular pool, with an apse-shaped extension to the north and a fountain jet, was located in front of the triclinium. This pool was connected to a smaller marble basin between the couches of the triclinium. An excellent view of the garden was afforded from the large salon at the rear of the tablinum with two columns at the entrance of the portico. The oecus also opened on the north portico with a fine view of the garden and the loggia above had a view of the garden as well as views to the sea and the Lattari Mountains.
Dates Excavated 1912, 1915, 1926 and 1936.
Bibliography Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, pp. 92. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, pp. 37. (worldcat)
Maiuri, A. 1929. NSc, p. 386, and fig. 18 (plan of triclinium) on p. 387, and fig. 20 (plan) on p. 389.
Maiuri, A. 1971. Pompeii, pp. 100-101. (worldcat)
Pernice, E. and Winter, F. 1925, Gefässe und Geräthe aus BronzeDie Hellenistische Kunst in Pompeii, p. 13.
Soprano, P. 1950. &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, p. 307, no. 30.
Spinazzola, V. 1910-1923. Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, p. 299 and fig. 334 (plan) on p. 297.
Warscher, T. 1937-1957. Codex Topographicus Pompeianus, appendix on water and photo no. 66.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 April 2021</description></item></channel></rss>