<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>lararia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/lararia/</link><description>Recent content in lararia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 10:01:33 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/lararia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I.6.13 House of Stallus Eros</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.13/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 10:01:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.13/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
Keywords fences (site elements) lararia Garden House of Stallus Eros.
Garden Description At the rear of this house a masonry wall surrounded the small garden which was undergoing extensive repairs at the time of the eruption. A lararium niche was located on the east wall and the rear wall held remnants of a garden painting. This painting was evidently in poor condition at the time of the eruption. Maiuri mentions the painting in his excavation report: “una grande parete dipinta con una pittura di paesaggio.” A detailed description is given by Della Corte who stated that the viridarium was given the illusion of enlargement by the paintings of woodland trees and flowering plants. He reported the usual lattice fence painted in the foreground with a tetrastyle pavilion and a statue of a winged female sphinx painted at each end of the fence. Oscilla were painted to appear to hang from the upper border of the large wall. A painting of Orpheus charming the beasts was barely visible on the right side of the wall. Seated on a dark red cloak between gigantic rocks in a landscape, his lyre against his leg, a variety of animals approached him. A section of the painting that survived on the right depicted a peacock, a goose, a cock, a wild boar, and a large black guinea hen. The painting was photographed at the time of excavation in 1929 (Mus. Naz. negative C/1614). Jashemski examined this site in 1964 and found part of a narrow panel still visible to the right of the large panel, although covered by vines. This panel was separated from the rest by a dark vertical stripe. At the bottom a lattice fencehad daisy-like flowers growing through it, with both rounded and pointed petals. Above the fence two roughly painted cypress trees (Cupressus sempervirens L.) flank several bushes which are not Acacia vera as suggested by Grimal. Jashemski notes that Grimal wrote his description on the basis of one sentence of Maiuri and the Museo Nazionale photograph included in Maiuri’s report. He also had Warscher’s photograph of the sphinx detail from the large panel but could not identify where it was located in the large panel. Jashemski also speculated that it was likely there had been an identical narrow panel on the other side of the large panel, but all the plaster had fallen leaving no trace of decorations. The best preserved section of the painting that Jashemski found was a large bush painted on the left side of the large panel. The bush could not be identified by the form of the fruit and/or flowers but perched in the bush was a crudely depicted owl identified as Athene noctua (Scopoli, 1769) by way of its big head and hefty legs. Another bird was painted on a higher branch to the right which may have been a thrush. Another bush just below and to the right edge of the painting and a large cypress to the right of the bush with the owl was shown in the Museo Nazionale (negative C/1614).
Plans Dates Excavated 1926 and 1927.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 25, no. 38.
de Vos, M. 1977. Meded, 39, p. 39.
Della Corte, M. NSc (1914), p. 269.
Grimal, P. 1969. Les jardins romaines, p. 446, no. 3. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, pp. 36, 313-314. (worldcat). Maiuri, A. 1929. NSc, pp. 434, fig. 44 (plan) on p. 432 and fig. 45.
PPP, 1, p. 39.
Schefold, K. and Dräyer, W. 1956. Pompeji, p. 26.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 April 2021</description></item><item><title>I.4.22</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.iv.22/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 12:52:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.iv.22/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
Keywords atrium triclinium Garden Garden with a triclinium at the rear of a domestic property.
Garden Description Directly to the rear of the atrium, a small viridarium with a paved space (1.70 x 2.50m) behind it suggested use as a summer triclinium to Fiorelli. Soprano was certain that there was an outdoor triclinium of wood or other material located here.
Bibliography Fiorelli, G. 1860. Giornale degli scavi di Pompei, p. 69 Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, p. 68 (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 32 (worldcat)
Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. II, p. 80 Soprano, P. 1950, &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, Napoli, Gaetano Macchiaroli, Editore, p. 308, no.36
Schefold, K. and Dräyer, W. 1956. Pompeji, p. 307, no. 29 (also incorrectly calls the garden a room)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Excavated 1858 and 1862
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 19 March 2021</description></item><item><title>I.4.11 Caupona of Copious</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.iv.11/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 12:45:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.iv.11/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
Keywords lararia cauponae Garden Garden at the rear of the Caupona of Copious.
Garden Description This modest caupona had a garden at the rear that was raised one step higher than the rest of the building. It once had a masonry altar with a lararium painting above but both of these have been lost. A latrine was located at the southeast corner of the garden.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 25, no.31 (worldcat) (incorrectly calls the garden a room)
Fiorelli, G. 1860. Giornale degli scavi di Pompei, p. 68 Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, p. 66 (worldcat)
W. F. Jashemski, 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, p. 171 (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 32 (worldcat)
Schefold, K. and Dräyer, W. 1956. Pompeji, p. 17 (also incorrectly calls the garden a room)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Excavated 1853 and 1863
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 19 March 2021</description></item><item><title>I.4.9</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.iv.9/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 12:38:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.iv.9/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
Keywords lararia tablina Garden Viridarium garden in a domestic property.
Garden Description This garden contains a cistern opening and form the entrance a viridarium at the rear of the tablinum and a niche lararium are clearly visible.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 24, no.30 (worldcat) Fiorelli, G. 1860. Giornale degli scavi di Pompei, p. 68 Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, p. 66 (worldcat) Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 34 (worldcat)
Niccolini, F. Le case ed i monumenti di Pompeii, Naples, Vol. II, p. 79
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Excavated 1855 and 1861
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 19 March 2021</description></item><item><title>House of the Garden of Hercules (II.viii.6)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords aedicula lararia strigillation triclinia dolium Garden Description A large aedicula lararium on the east wall and a large triclinium (l. medius, 4.40 m.; l. imus 4.00; l. summus 3.80 m.; table between couches 1.00 x 1.67m.) were found in the large area attached to this humble house when excavation was started in 1953-1954. Human remains were uncovered with five gold coins, two gold rings, a strigil and seven medical instruments close to the -triclinium. Next to the shrine two terra-cotta votive offerings, a slender female winged figure (0.155 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10569) and a small draped figure with considerable red paint surviving on the drapery(figure (0.165 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10150) were found as well as a marble statuette of Hercules (ca. 0.57 high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 10138). South of the triclinium a doghouse had been built by mounting half of a dolium (0.70 x 0.50m.) on a masonry base 0.15 m. high. Further finds included a large terra-cotta funnel, but the function of this area could not be determined. Excavation by Jashemski in 1971-1972 revealed what appears to be a large commercial flower garden. Where the lapilli remained until the 1970s, the undamaged soil contours and root and stake cavities were well preserved. Circular watering depressions remained in one bed that held a small plant. Balloon photographs showed complicated bed arrangements and a path coming from the outside area to the middle of the garden where a left turn led to the triclinium and altar in front of the lararium. Fig.63, 17.7.73, Fig. 64, 8.33.73, Fig. 65, 21A.13.73 An extensive system of rain water collection and distribution had been built. Roof run off was collected in a large dolium on each side of the door and in a nearby pool. Additional water could be brought from outside sources and poured through an amphora tip in the east end of the north wall to fill a dolium](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300400601) imbedded in the northeast corner of the garden. The natural slope of the land was from north to south and the irrigation layout took advantage of this fact. When the dolium](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300400601) in the northeast corner overflowed the water ran down a channel along the east wall watering young trees planted in the channel until it fell into a second half dolium](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300400601) buried in the soil. This process would be repeated the length of the east wall and continued along the south wall. There were channels along the north and west walls and dividing all the beds in the interior of the garden. Eleven large tree root cavities were counted with dimensions of 30 cm. or more at ground level. One grew near the southwest corner of the shrine, three along the walls and seven scattered about the garden. Another huge, partially destroyed cavity about 2 m. could have been an olive tree that grew to the west of the cistern. Many other smaller tree root cavities were found, and carbonized cherries (Prunus cerasus L.) that were found here would identify at least some of these. Along the walls with the tree root cavities were terra-cotta pots similar to those found in the House of the Ship Europa (I.XV.1-3). There were well preserved vine root cavities and post cavities for the pergola over the triclinium. Most of the garden cavities that remained were for the stakes that supported the frames for the shade structures for young bedding plants. Parallel to the west wall, 3.30m away from it, a row of posts formed either a shed or an arbor with roofing support holes in the wall above. Two ancient gardening tools, a sarculum and a dolabella were found in the garden along with bones, teeth, perfume bottle fragments, and fragments of terra-cotta unguent containers. The house to this garden contained a large number of glass perfume bottles. The assessment of pollen and spores found here are shown in Jashemski (1979).
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1953-1954, 1971-1972.
Bibliography Jashemski, W. 1979. The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden, American Journal of Archaeology, 83 (worldcat) Jashemski, W. 1979. Gardens of Pompeii, vol.I, pp.279-288 and figs. 421-435 (worldcat) Jashemski, W. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii, vol.II, pp.94-95 (worldcat) Meyer, F.G. 1980. Carbonized food plants of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villa at Torre Annunziata, p.432 Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 11 March 2021</description></item><item><title>I.7.7 House of the Priest Amandus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.7/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 16:01:37 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vii.7/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
Keywords aedicules atriums cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) lararia peristyles (columnades) porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia Gardens House of the Priest Amandus.
Garden Description One step above the level of the triclinium of this small house with an irregular floor plan was a peristyle garden. It was to the west of the atrium and enclosed on the north and east by a portico. Five columns supported the portico and two engaged columns on the west wall continued the order of the peristyle. A large tree root cavity (the cast measures 0.80 x 0.82) indicated that the garden was well shaded and nail holes in the wall would suggest that vines had been trained to grow in that area. A large window located in the room to the west gave a view into the garden. A puteal was located over the cistern opening in the northwest corner of the peristyle and another puteal was additionally found in the garden as well as a cartibulum (tables) decorated on one side with lions heads and a small circular base most likely used for a statuette. A lararia] on the west wall consisted of an aedicula façade with an arched niche.
Dates Excavated 1912 and 1924.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 25, no. 39.
Jashemski, W.F. 1979. Garden of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius, p. 30. (worldcat)
Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, pp. 37-38. (worldcat)
Maiuri, A. 1939. NSc, pp. 26-27 and fig. 1 (plan) on p. 4.
Maiuri, A. 1939. Pompeii, p. 112. (worldcat)
Maiuri, A. 1961. “I giardini,” In Le Vie d’Italia, p. 1138, no. 9.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 April 2021</description></item><item><title>I.6.2 House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 19:15:13 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.vi.2/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
Keywords archaeological garden atriums busts (sculpture) columns (architectural elements) cryptoportici lararia loggias mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes stairs Garden House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus.
Garden Description A. A passageway from the atrium led to a modest peristyle garden visible through a window in the rear wall. A low wall enclosed the garden on the north and east sides along with five brick columns covered with white stucco and a pillar supporting the roof of the portico. A large, well preserved wall painting survived on the west wall of the north portico as well as a niche lararium decorated with a painted bust of Mercury. From the garden a flight of stairs led down to an elegant cryptoporticus(underground portico) illuminated by light from the adjacent garden through high windows. A solarium terrace, or loggia, overlooking the large garden could be reached by another flight of stairs form the east portico.
B. At the rear of the house, a large enclosed garden had been increased in size by reducing the wings of the cryptoporticus. The last owner had built a spacious loggia (5 x 20 m.) above the north wing of the cryptoporticus overlooking the garden. A high wall joined the five pillars and the roof supporting pilaster and formed windows into the garden. At the west end of the loggia was a masonry triclinium with side couches, each having a fulcrum (foot), (l. medius 4.41m.; l.summus and l. imus 4.68 m.; dia. of table 0.55m.). A large area was left open for tables or dancers, suggesting to Spinoza that this could have been a public gathering place. There were low seats in front of the side couches and extended along the terrace walls that may have been intended for children according to Soprano. A kitchen was located on the north side of the loggia. Six steps from the southeast corner of the loggia led up into the garden which had been raised to the level of the windows in the cryptoporticus. Della Corte thought that this garden had been used to raise many cabbages and leeks. The remains of eleven victims of the volcanic eruption were found in the garden.
Dates Excavated 1911-1929.
Bibliography Della Corte, M. NSc (1914), pp. 74-75, 228. Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, pp. 452-453. (worldcat) Jashemski, W.F. 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, pp. 33-34. (worldcat) Maiuri, A. 1933. NSc, pp. 256, 258-259, 272 and pl. 5 (plan). Prina Ricotti, S.P. Cucine Romana a Pompei E Come Eseguirle, pp. 268-271. Soprano, P. 1950, &amp;lsquo;I triclini all’aperto di Pompei&amp;rsquo;, In Pompeiana, raccolta di studi per il secondo centenario degli scavi di Pompei, Napoli, Gaetano Macchiaroli, Editore, pp. 294-295, no. 4 and fig. 30. (worldcat) Spinazzola, V. 1914. NSc, pp. 256, 259-262, 287, 365-368. Spinazzola, V. 1910-1923, Pompei alla luce degli Scavi Nuovi di Via dell&amp;rsquo;Abbondanza, pp. 121-122, 442, 444-445, 451, 453. (worldcat) Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 16. Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 April 2021</description></item><item><title>I.5.3/16</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.v.3/16/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 16:34:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/i.v.3/16/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
Garden Hospitium garden, possibly planted in antiquity.
Keywords archaeological garden lararia stables (animal housing) troughs (containers) Garden Description This site had been destroyed in antiquity and probably had been a hospitium. Excavated in 1874, the remains of a watering trough for animals and a stable were uncovered. Often demolished sites were planted but it could not be determined if there was vegetation present at the time of the eruption. The west wall contained an arched lararium niche.
Dates Excavated 1874.
Bibliography Boyce, G.K. 1937. Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, p. 25, no. 34. Fiorelli, G. 1875. Descrizione di Pompei, pp. 452-453. (worldcat) Jashemski, W.F. 1993. Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Vol. II, Appendices, p. 33. (worldcat) Viola, L. 1879. Gli scavi di Pompei dal 1873 al 1878, p. 16. Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 31 March 2021</description></item></channel></rss>