<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tablinium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/tablinium/</link><description>Recent content in tablinium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/tablinium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>House of Championnet I</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_viii/insula_ii/house_of_championnet_i/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/pompeii/region_viii/insula_ii/house_of_championnet_i/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region VIII
Insula Insula II
House House I
Keywords tablinium portico Garden Description This house was excavated in 1799 and to the rear of the tablinium there was a portico which enclosed an area surrounded by a gutter. Openings were cut in the floor where the twelve supporting columns stood to allow light into the rooms below in the volcanic ledge. Mazois and Fiorelli labeled this area a hanging garden because of this configuration. A grand view of the Bay of Naples and the mountains could be enjoyed from the terraces on two levels in this house, and potted plants and shrubs may have been placed there.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Excavation Dates 1799
Bibliography Boyce, Corpus of the Lararia of Pompeii, Memoris of the American Academy in Rome, 1937, p.74 (worldcat) Breton, Pompeia, 3rd ed. p.502 (worldcat) Dyer, Pompeii, 3rd ed. p.441 (worldcat) Dyer, Pompeii, p.442 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol. II, p. 205 (worldcat) Maiuri, Notizie degli scavi di Antichita, 1933, p.272 (worldcat) Mazois, Les ruines de Pompei dessinees et mesurees pendant les annees, 1809-1810-1811, 2:62 and pls. 21 (plan), 22 (worldcat) Niccolini, Antonio, Fausto, and Felice, Le case ed i monumenti di Pompei designati e descritti, vol. 3, “Topografia,” pl. 6 (plan) (worldcat) Noack and Lehmann-Hartleben, Baugeschichtliche Untersuchungen am Stadtrand von Pompeji, pp. 114-121 passim and figs. 32 on p. 116, 33 on p. 117 (plans) and pl. 17 (plan), pl. 26 (reconstruction) (worldcat) Fiorelli,ed. Pompeianarum Antiquitatum Historia, May 16, 1800, vol. 1, pt.2, p 173 (worldcat) Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 Februray 2021</description></item><item><title>Casa del Salone Nero (VI.13/11)</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_vi/house_13/casa_del_salone_nero/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_vi/house_13/casa_del_salone_nero/</guid><description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula VI
House House 13
Garden Casa del Salone Nero
Keywords porticos tablinium Garden Description Excavation of this garden (a) to the rear of this elegant house took place in the spring of 1939. The garden was completely surround by a portico which had eight columns and two pillars on the north side with engaged columns placed strategically so as to provide an unimpeded view from the tablinum. The southwest corner of the garden was the location of a small pool (0.82 x 0.63).
Plans Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum) Herculaneum VI.11-19,25-26-Casa del Salone Nero Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 240 and fig. 187 (plan) on p. 239 (worldcat)
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description></item></channel></rss>