<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>temple on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/temple/</link><description>Recent content in temple on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 21:57:14 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/tags/temple/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Vigna Barberini</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/rome/vigna_barberini/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 21:57:14 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/rome/vigna_barberini/</guid><description>Province ITALIA
ITALIA (Pleiades)
ITALIA, REGIO I (Pleiades)
Province Description Location Rome
Rome (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Palatine Hill
Palatine Hill (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description Garden Gardens of the House of Augustus, PalatineKeywords domus palaces peristyle (Roman courtyards) temple Garden Description The artificial terrace that now carries the Barberini family name is located on the northeastern corner of the Palatine, beyond the visible remains of the Flavian Imperial palace (Fig. 1). Excavations carried out during the 1930s by A. Bartoli, and in the 1950s by G. F. Carettoni concentrated primarily on the central area of this site. These campaigns revealed the foundations of a large temple, which Bartoli identified, consistent with the earlier ideas of P. Bigot, as the remains of the late second-century Temple of Elagabalus.
Recent investigations by the Soprintendenza Archeologica in collaboration with École française de Rome have revealed further episodes of the history of the area.
Approximately one third of the site has been explored, although the most ancient levels have been reached only sporadically (Fig. 2). The information gathered during the campaigns carried out annually between 1985 and 1999 are at present being analyzed, with the result that some of the information presented here must be considered provisional. The excavations that reached levels prior to the rise of the Empire revealed a peristyle of a large domus once decorated with plants and basins. Probably destroyed during the 60s of the first century CE, this luxurious dwelling was then buried under thick layers of soil used to create an artificial terrace that was a grand garden of the Palace of Domitian. About a century later, during the last years of the second century, this section of the Imperial palace was demolished to make room for a monumental complex centered around a temple dedicated by the emperor Heliogabalus to the eastern god, Elagabalus, later rededicated by Severus Alexander to Jupiter Ultor.
Figures Figure 1. Aerial photograph of the Vigna Barberini taken early 1999.. Figure 2. Vigna Barberini: plan of the areas explored from 1985 to 1998.. Dates 1st century BCE- 2nd century CE
Bibliography P. Bigot, “Le temple de Jupiter Ultor et la Vigna Barberini,” BullCom 1911, pp. 80-85.(worldcat) F. Villedieu, J.-P Morel, P. Pergola, H. Broise, Y. Thébert, P. Gros, E. Hubert, et alii, “Rome: le Palatin (Vigna Barberini),” Mélanges de l’École Française de Rome 98 (1986) pp. 387-396; 99 (1987) pp. 481-498; 100 (1988) pp. 505-525; 101 (1989) pp. 489-498; 102 (1990) pp. 443-471; 103 (1991) pp. 313-338; 104 (1992) pp. 465-493; 105 (1993) pp. 419-439; 106 (1994) pp. 431-450; 107 (1995) pp. 459-493; 108 (1996) pp. 423-451; 109 (1997) pp. 417-440; 110 (1998) pp. 473-492; 111 (1999) pp. 449-481; 112 (2000) pp. 413-432.(worldcat) M. Royo, F. Chausson, E. Hubert, et alii, La Vigna Barberini I. Histoire d’un site. Étude des sources et de la topographie, Rome, 1997.(worldcat) M.A. Tomei, “La ex Vigna Barberini e le aree limitrofe: documentazione dall’archivio della Soprintendenza archeologica” La Vigna Barberini I, op. cit, pp. 191-210.(worldcat) C. Virlouvet, F. Villedieu, et alii, “Fouilles de l’École française de Rome sur le site de la Vigna Barberini (Palatin),” Bollettino di Archeologia 23-24 (1993), pp. 131-164.(worldcat) F. Villedieu, “La Vigna Barberini (Palatino): nuove acquisizioni,” Archeologia Laziale XII, Quaderni di Archeologia Etrusco-italica, 1995, pp. 33-39.(worldcat) F. Villedieu, “Constructions impériales mises au jour à l&amp;rsquo;angle N-E du Palatin. Résultats des fouilles de l&amp;rsquo;École française de Rome sur le site de la Vigna Barberini,” Comptes Rendus de l’Académie des Inscriptions &amp;amp; Belles-Lettres, 1995, pp. 719-736.(worldcat) J.-P. Morel, “Stratigraphie et histoire sur le Palatin : la zone centrale de la Vigna Barberini,” Comptes Rendus de l’Académie des Inscriptions &amp;amp; Belles-Lettres, 1996, pp. 173-205.(worldcat) F. Villedieu, P. Veltri, “Les soutènements nord-ouest et nord de la terrasse de la Vigna Barberini (Rome, Palatin): constructions et remaniements de l’époque flavienne à l’époque sévérienne,” Mélanges de l’École Française de Rome, 111 (1999), pp. 749-778.(worldcat) F. Villedieu , et alii, Il giardino dei Cesari. Exhibition catalogue (Rome, Museo Nazionale Romano, Terme di Diocleziano, Oct. 2001- Jan. 2002), Rome, 2001.(worldcat) Pleiades ID Palatine Hill (Pleiades)
Contributor Françoise VilledieuORCID Publication date 15 APRIL 2021</description></item><item><title>Gardens of the Temple of the Divine Claudius</title><link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/rome/temple_claudii_divi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 10:57:44 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/province/italia/rome/temple_claudii_divi/</guid><description>Province ITALIA
ITALIA (Pleiades)
ITALIA, REGIO I (Pleiades)
Province Description Location Rome
Rome (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Caelian Hill
Caelian Hill (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description Garden Gardens of the Temple of Divine Claudius, Palatine
Keywords aqueducts cisterns (plumbing components) nemus (grove) niches (architectural elements) nymphaea (garden structures) porticoes planting beds stagnum (man-made lake) temple Garden Description The Temple of the Divine Claudius, located on the northern slope of the Caelian Hill, was constructed in multiple phases. The temple is known from the Severan marble plan (FUR) (Fig. 1) and from archaeological remains. Agrippina initiated the building of the temple but was murdered before its completion. After the fire of 64 CE, Nero altered the temple to include it in the Domus Aurea (Seutonius Vesp. 9; Frontinus Aq. 2.76). Vespasian completed the temple in 69 CE.
The temple is located on top of a platform (180 x 210 m.) and is situated just off-center to the east. During Nero&amp;rsquo;s reign, the platform upon which the temple stood was converted into a nymphaeum as part of the Domus Aurea, which the Aqua Claudia supplied. Nero redirected the Aqua Claudia to feed the stagnum of the Domus Aurea. The rectangular and semi-circular niches on the eastern side are best preserved and are visible from the Via Claudia. The space between this façade and the platform wall proper is presumably a passage for water. Vespasian restored the temple and Claudius' divinity in 69 CE and considerably altered the original structure. Fragment 5c of FUR, now existing only as a Renaissance drawing, depicts the temple as a prostyle, pentastyle temple. However, most scholars agree that the temple was probably hexastyle.
Because these remains are located under the present-day Monastery of the Passionist Fathers, no recent excavation has been possible. A. M. Colini’s excavations reveal that the four faces of the platform differ significantly. Under the stairs of the north side was a cistern, presumably remnants of Nero&amp;rsquo;s nymphaeum, the water supply for the temple complex. The south face, as yet unexcavated, should reveal evidence of the Aqua Claudia.
The temple is set within eight L-shaped [planting beds](http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300430426 and fourteen rectangular planting beds (Fig. 2). Some scholars considered these forms to be the substructures of the temple complex, while it is also possible that these structures are water features. However, the majority of scholars believe that these structures are planted rows of trees or shrubs in a nemus, similar to the plantings found during the new excavations of the Templum Pacis. The role of Vespasian as sponsor also lends credence to such an interpretation. Vespasian is credited with building a quadriporticus to surround the entire platform and Martial mentions a porticus (Martial Sp. 2.9-10), but there is no evidence for the porticus on the marble plan.
Dates 1st century CE
Bibliography M. Blake, Roman Construction in Italy from Tiberius through the Flavians. Washington, 1959, pp. 31-3, 52-3, 90-1. (worldcat) LTUR, s.v. Claudius, Divus, Templum by C. Buzzetti; (worldcat) A.M. Colini, MemPontAcc 7 (1994): 137-62. (worldcat) R.H. Darwall-Smith, Emperors and Architecture: A Study of Flavian Rome. Bruxelles, 1996, pp. 48-55, pl. 4-5. (worldcat) R. Lloyd, &amp;ldquo;Three Monumental Gardens on the Marble Plan&amp;rdquo; American Journal of Archaeology (1986): 91-100. (worldcat) K. Gleason and L. Cockerham, &amp;ldquo;Rus in Urbe: Two Parks of Ancient Rome&amp;rdquo; CELA Proceedings, 1992, pp. 103-12.(worldcat) Pleiades ID Caelian Hill (Pleiades)
TGN ID 7000874
Contributor Valerie AymerORCID Publication date &amp;lt;15 APRIL 2021&amp;gt;</description></item></channel></rss>